Guide to the Renata Gorczynski Papers Relating to Czeslaw Milosz
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Renata Gorczynski papers relating to Czesław Miłosz
1934-1998
GEN MSS 528
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.09
(6 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, and other material documenting the personal and professional relationship between Gorczynski and Czesław Miłosz. Series I, Correspondence, is organized into subseries for Miłosz, Gorczynski and Third-Party correspondence. The Miłosz correspondence contains several folders of correspondence with Gorczynski, dating from 1979-1991, as well as holograph drafts of outgoing letters and single incoming letters with other writers, friends, publishers, and institutions. Other correspondents include Lars Gyllensten, Östen Sjöstrand, Wacław Korabiewicz, Jadwiga Stańczakowa, and André de Vincenz. The Gorczynski correspondence consists of incoming letters from Stanisław Barańczak, Maria Janion, Piotr Kłoczowski, Ryszard Przybylski, and Tomas Venclova. Series II, Writings, is organized into subseries for the writings of Miłosz, Gorczynski, and others. The Miłosz writings include essays and lectures, poetry, translations, and other writings. There are holograph drafts of essays and lectures, including drafts in English and Polish for the Charles Eliot Norton lectures delivered in 1981-82, and numerous corrected copies of poems. The Gorczynski writings contain corrected typescript drafts of books edited by Gorczynski and several interviews with Miłosz. Series III, Other Material, contains audio recordings, photographs, and other papers.
Other Storage Formats: Audio Recordings
Gorczynski, Renata
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Renata Gorczynski Papers Relating to Czeslaw Milosz were acquired through gifts from Renata Gorczynski between 1991-1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 6: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Scope and Contents
The Renata Gorczynski Papers Relating to Czeslaw Milosz consist of letters, manuscripts, and personal papers documenting the personal and professional relationship between Gorcznyski and Czeslaw Milosz. The collection spans the years 1934-1991, with the bulk of the papers dating from the 1980s.
The collection is housed in 6 boxes and organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Material. Box 6 contains Restricted Fragile Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: Czeslaw Milosz Correspondence, Renata Gorczynski Correspondence, and Third-Party Correspondence.
The Milosz correspondence, housed in box 1, includes correspondence with writers, friends, publishers, and institutions. The correspondence, which dates predominantly from the early 1980s, provides some evidence of how the author's life was effected by his reception of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1980. Most folders consist of a single holograph draft of a letter from Milosz or a single incoming letter. There are outgoing drafts of letters to American President Jimmy Carter, Lars Gyllensten, Bill Moyers, and Östen Sjöstrand, and incoming letters from Waclaw Korabiewicz, Jadwiga Stanczakowa, and Andre de Vincenz, as well as American and Polish institutions. In addition, there are several folders of correspondence between Milosz and Gorczynski.
The Renata Gorczynski correspondence, housed in box 2, dates from 1986-87, and consists of incoming letters from Stanislaw Baranczak, Maria Janion, Piotr Kloczowski, Ryszard Przybylski, and Tomas Venclova. Third-Party Correspondence, also housed in box 2, includes copies of letters from Lech Walesa.
Series II, Writings, housed in boxes 3-5, is organized into three subseries: Writings of Czeslaw Milosz, Writings of Renata Gorczynski, and Writings of Others. The writings of Czeslaw Milosz are subdivided for essays and lectures, poetry, translations, and other writings. The materials include numerous holograph drafts of essays and lectures, including drafts in English and Polish for the Charles Eliot Norton lectures, delivered at Harvard in 1981-82 and published as The Witness of Poetry (1983). The Writings include individual poems and three poetry collections: Dalsze okolice, Trzy zimy, and "Wiersze, noty, epigraphy." Trzy zimy (1987) is a re-edition of Milosz's second collection, with essays by Polish literary critics. "Wiersze, noty, epigraphy" is a collection of poems and translations. Individual poems and collections are present chiefly in the form of corrected copies.
Writings of Renata Gorczynski includes drafts for two books edited by Gorczynski, Conversations with Czeslaw Milosz (1987) and Listy do Czeslawa Milosza, 1952-1979 (1992). The latter is a collection of letters to Milosz from Zygmunt Hertz. These drafts are followed by materials for interviews with Milosz, as well as typescripts of actual conversations with the poet.
Writings of Others consists chiefly of photocopies of poems.
Series III, Other Material, housed in box 5, is organized into subseries for Material Relating to Czeslaw Milosz and Miscellaneous Material. Material Relating to Czeslaw Milosz consists of personal papers, such as addresses, itineraries, lists, and notes, as well as several snapshots and a commercial audio recording of Milosz reading both from his own work and the work of Mickiewicz. Miscellaneous Material consists of a commercial audio recording of readings from Mickiewicz's Pan Tadeusz and photographs of Zbigniew Herbert's apartment.
Restricted Fragile Papers are housed in box 6.
Authors, Polish -- 20th Century -- Archives; European literature -- 20th Century; Polish literature -- 20th Century; Poland; Photographic prints; Authors; Barańczak, Stanisław, 1946-2014; Gorczynski, Renata; Gyllensten, Lars, 1921-2006; Janion, Maria, 1926-; Kłoczowski, Piotr; Korabiewicz, Wacław; Miłosz, Czesław, 1911-2004; Przybylski, Ryszard, 1928-; Sjöstrand, Östen, 1925-; Stańczakowa, Jadwiga; Venclova, Tomas, 1937-; Vincenz, André de
- Correspondence, 1952-1991; Series I; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: Czeslaw Milosz Correspondence, Renata Gorczynski Correspondence, and Third Party Correspondence.
  - CZESLAW MILOSZ CORRESPONDENCE
    - Bromberg, Adam, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Carter, Jimmy, 1924-, 1980 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dartmouth College, 1983 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Duckworth, ----, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Ethics and Public Policy Center (Washington, D.C.), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "F" General, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fältheim, Ake, 1980 Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Copies of letters
    - Fédération nationale d'achats des cadres (France), 1983 Oct 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "G" General, 1983, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Giedroyc, Jerzy, 1983 Jul 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Gorczynski, Renata, 1979-91, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11-17)
      Includes enclosures and empty envelopes
    - Grygiel, Stanislaw, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Gyllensten, Lars, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - [Hughes, Robert?], 1982 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Copy of letter from Milosz to Hughes
    - "J" General, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Jankowski, K., 1982 Apr (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Includes poems
    - "K" General, 1983, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Korabiewicz, Waclaw, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "M" General, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Macmillan Publishing Company, 1980 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Moyers, [Bill D.?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Polska Akademia Nauk. Zaklad Narodowy imienia Ossolinskich, 1983 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "R" General, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Rosenthal, ----, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "S" General, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Sauzey, Francois, 1983 Sep 5 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Includes copy of "A Nation" by Milosz
    - [Sjöstrand?], Osten (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Stanczakowa, Jadwiga, 1983 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Szmunes, Helena, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Temenos, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Trilateral Commission, 1983 Jul 20 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - [University of California, Berkeley. Press?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Vincenz, Andre de, 1984 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - "W" General, 1983 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Walesa, Lech, 1983 Oct, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Includes draft of petition to President of Polish Council of State
    - Wankowicz, Melchior, 1952-56, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Copies of letters from Wankowicz
    - Weinfeld, David, 1981 Jan 17 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 1983 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Yale University. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures, 1983 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - "Z" General, 1982-83 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Unidentified, 1981-83, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Empty envelopes, 1979 Jan 10 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - RENATE GORCZYNSKI CORRESPONDENCE
    - Baranczak, Stanislaw, 1986 Sep 21 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Janion, Maria, 1987 Nov 1 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Kloczowski, Piotr, 1986-87 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Milosz, Czeslaw
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Series I. Czeslaw Milosz Correspondence, Box 1, folders 11-17
    - Przybylski, Ryszard, 1987 Nov 4 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Venclova, Tomas, 1986-87 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Unidentified, 1986, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Third-Party Correspondence
    - New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.) to Adam Michnik, 1983 Dec 12 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Walesa, Lech to Ethics and Public Policy Center (Washington, D.C.) (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Writings, 1934-1990; Series II; 1.04; (2.5 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into three subseries: Writings of Czeslaw Milosz, Writings of Renata Gorczynski, and Writings of Others.
  - WRITINGS OF CZESLAW MILOSZ
    - Essays and lectures
      - ["America is a difficult country..."], essay, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 58)
      - ["It is a great honor to be elected..."], lecture, draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 59)
      - "Jubilat," essay, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - "Notatki o wygnaniu," essay, drafts, typescript and typescript photocopy, corrected (Box 3, Folder 61)
        Polish translation by Renata Gorczynski
      - "O podboju," lecture, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 62)
      - "Pieniadz," essay, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 63)
      - ["Poezja moja dlugo byla uwazana..."], draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 64)
      - ["This book was written..."], holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 65)
      - ["W latach szescdziesiatych odbyla sie w Rzymie beatyfikacja Ojca Kolbe..."], essay, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 66)
      - The Witness of Poetry (Charles Eliot Norton lectures, Harvard University, 1981-1982)
        - Notebook, drafts, holograph, corrected (Polish), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 67)
          Includes "Struktura poezji" and "Poeci i rodzina ludzka"
        - "Za... od... Europy," draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 68)
        - "A Lesson of Biology," draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
        - [Poets and the Human Family], draft, holograph, corrected (Box 3, Folder 70)
        - [Starting from my Europe], draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - Untitled drafts, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Poetry
      Collections
      - Dalsze okolice, printout photocopy, corrected, 1984-90, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - Trzy zimy, photocopy, typescript, printout, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 74-78)
        Includes photocopies of poems and essays by Artur Miedzyrzecki, Stanislaw Baranczak, Tomas Venclova and others
      - "Wiersze, noty, epigrafy," typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 79)
        Includes poems and translations
      - Individual poems
        - "Ale ksiazki," draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 80)
        - "Bypassing Rue Descartes," drafts, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 81)
        - "Capri," draft, printout, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 82)
        - "Czlowiek-mucha," draft, printout, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 83)
        - "Do Allena Ginsberga," draft, printout, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 84)
        - "Do Heloizy," drafts, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 85)
        - "Do Lecha Walesa," draft, holograph, 1982 Mar (Box 4, Folder 86)
          See also: To Lech Walesa, Box 4, folder 110
        - "Dobranoc," typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 87)
        - "Dom filozofa," drafts, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 88)
          Includes "Komentarz do 'Domu filozofa'"
        - "Dwa wiersze," photocopy of printed version, corrected, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 89)
          Includes "Rozmowa z Jeanne" and "Wiersz na koniec stulecia" and note, dated 20 Nov 1990, in unidentified hand
        - ["For some hundred years that fabric, fleecy..."], drafts, typescript, corrected (Box 4, Folder 90)
        - "Fotografia," draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 91)
        - "The Gates of the Arsenal," draft, typescript, corrected, [1934?] (Box 4, Folder 92)
        - "Godzina," draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 93)
        - ["Jakie to glupie, panstwo i jego dzielo..."], draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 94)
        - ["Kronikarz oddycha, serce jego bije..."], draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 95)
        - "Lumen," draft, typescript photocopy, corrected (Box 4, Folder 96)
        - "Medytacja," draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 97)
        - "Moce," draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 98)
        - "Na plazy," draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 99)
        - "Nastepca," draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 100)
        - "Odczyt," draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 101)
        - "Oset, pokrzywa," draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 102)
        - "Pajak," draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 103)
        - "Poblazanie," draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 104)
        - "Sens," draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 105)
        - "The Separate Notebook: Wormwood Star," drafts, typescript, holograph, and photocopies, corrected (Box 4, Folder 106)
        - "The Song," draft, typescript corrected, [1934?] (Box 4, Folder 107)
        - "Song on Porcelain," draft, printout (new translation), [1947?] (Box 4, Folder 108)
        - "Suknia w groszki," draft, printout, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 109)
        - "To Lech Walesa," draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 110)
          See also: Do Lecha Walesa, Box 4, folder 86
        - "Trwalosc," draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 111)
        - "W muzyce," draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 112)
        - "W pewnym wieku," draft, printout corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 113)
        - "W Yale," draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 114)
        - ["W zapachu czabrow, na pagorku...], draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 115)
        - "Wcielony," draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 116)
        - "Wdowiec," draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 117)
        - "Zbieranie moreli," draft, typescript, photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 118)
        - ["Zadnego z utopionych w naszym miescie kociat..."], draft fragment, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 119)
        - Untitled drafts, holograph and photocopy, corrected (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Translations
      - Book of Revelation, 1:1 to 22:21, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 121)
      - Individual poems, typescript photocopy (Box 4, Folder 122)
      - Poems from "A Zen Harvest", photocopy of printed version, Tygodnik Powszechny, 1990 Dec 2 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Other Writings
      - ["A zarazem lektura grubego skryptu..."], fragment from a journal, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 124)
      - ["Bardzo trudno jest przetlumaczyc..."] note on translation, typescript, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 125)
      - ["Czeslaw Milosz was born..."], autobiographical statement, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 126)
      - "Fragments from a Journal," photocopy of printed version, Antaeus, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 127)
      - Interview, printout photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 128)
      - ["Polska literatura, muzyka..."], autobiographical note, holograph, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - WRITINGS OF RENATA GORCZYNSKI
    - Works edited by Renata Gorczynski
      - Conversations with Czeslaw Milosz, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 130)
      - Letters from Zygmunt Hertz to Czeslaw Milosz, printout, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 131)
        Includes corrections by Milosz
      - Trzy zimy, outline, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Interviews with Czeslaw Milosz
      - Dolina Issy, notes, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 133)
      - Interviews for "Tygodnik Polski", 1980 Sep, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 134)
        Includes "O przekladach tekstow biblijnych i godnosci slowa" and "O nowych publikacjach i godnosci Polakow"
      - ["Mysmy za malo rozmawiali o 'Trzech zimach'..."], typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 135)
      - "O przekladach tekstow biblijnych i godnosci slowa," drafts, typescript and typescript photocopy, corrected, 1980 Sep (Box 5, Folder 136)
      - "Rozmowa o ambasadzie," typescript, corrected, 1981 Jan 11 (Box 5, Folder 137)
      - Zniewolony umysl, notes, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 138)
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Aaron, Jonathan
      - "The Collected Poems," review, photocopy of printed version, Harvard Book Review, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Bialoszewski, Miron
      - Poems, photocopies of printed versions, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Czechowicz, Jozef
      - "Ta chwila," poem, photocopy of printed version, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - Fallain, Jean
      - "Muzyka sfer," poem, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Gregg, Linda
      - "Dorosla," poem, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Herbert, Zbigniew
      - "Kamyk," poem, photocopy of printed version, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - Maj, Bronislaw
      - Poems, photocopies of printed versions, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Scott, Peter Dale
      - "Letter to a Poet," poem, typescript photocopy, 1982 Oct 27 (Box 5, Folder 146)
        Includes annotations by Milosz
    - Stafford, William
      - "Wakacje," poem, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Transtromer, Tomas
      - Poems, typescript photocopies, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Vendler, Helen
      - "A World Perfect at Last," essay, typescript, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - Wagoner, David
      - Poems, typescript photocopies, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - Wat, Aleksander
      - Poems, photocopies of printed versions, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 151)
    - Weores, Sandor
      - "Deszcz," poem, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 152)
    - Wonk, Dalt
      - "Czeslaw Milosz. Poetry, Politics and a Quiet Fame," article, printed version, Tulanian, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 153)
        Includes note in hand of Milosz
    - Wormser, Baron
      - "Grave Combats," review, photocopy of printed version, Parnassus, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 154)
    - Zagajewski, Adam
      - Poems, photocopies of printed versions, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 155)
    - Unidentified
      - "Kronika krajowa," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 156)
      - Master's thesis on Czeslaw Milosz (incomplete), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 157)
      - "Oscar Milosz and the Vision of the Cosmos," typescript photocopy, corrected (Box 5, Folder 158)
      - "River," poem, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 159)
- Other Material, 1980-1998; Series III; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Series III, Other Material, is organized into two subseries: Material Relating to Czeslaw Milosz and Miscellaneous Material
  - MATERIAL RELATING TO CZESLAW MILOSZ
    - Addresses, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 160)
    - Copy of letter to Maria Prozor in Milosz's hand (Box 5, Folder 161)
      Letter dated 28 Octobre 1920
    - Invoice for air travel, 1980 Dec 3 (Box 5, Folder 162)
    - Itineraries, 1980-82, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 163)
    - Lists, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 164)
    - "Milosz cyzta Mickiewicza/Milosz cyzta Milosza" [Sound Recording], 1996 (Box 5, Folder 165)
    - Miscellaneous notes in Milosz's hand (Box 5, Folder 166)
    - Photograph of honorary degree, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 167)
    - Photographs of Milosz, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 168-169)
    - Presentation for National Medal of Arts, 1989 Nov 17 (Box 5, Folder 170)
    - Printed material relating to American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters ceremonial, 1982 May 19 (Box 5, Folder 171)
  - MISCELLANEOUS MATERIAL
    - "Marathon z "Panem Tadeuszem" na BIS" [Sound Recording], 1998 (Box 5, Folder 172)
    - Photographs of Zbigniew Herbert's apartment, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 173)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 9 (Box 6, Folder 174)
  - Box 1, folder 15 (Box 6, Folder 175)
  - Box 4, folder 85 (Box 6, Folder 176)